<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<component>
    <name>Cutadapt</name>
    <version>1.8</version>
    <doc>Replace &quot;ADAPTER&quot; with the actual sequence of your 3&apos; adapter. IUPAC wildcard characters are supported. The reverse complement is *not* automatically searched. All reads from the input FASTX (FASTQ or FASTA) will be written to the output FASTX with the adapter sequence removed. Adapter matching is error-tolerant. Multiple adapter sequences can be given (use further --adapter options), but only the best-matching adapter will be removed. Compressed input and output is supported and auto-detected from the file name (.gz, .xz, .bz2). Various other adapter types (5&apos; adapters, &quot;mixed&quot; 5&apos;/3&apos; adapters etc. are supported, as well as trimming of a fixed number of bases, quality trimming, trimming of paired-end reads, trimming colorspace reads and the filtering of reads by various criteria.</doc>
    <author email="marcel.martin@scilifelab.se">Marcel Martin</author>
    <category>NGS analysis</category>
    <category>read extraction</category>
    <launcher type="python">
        <argument name="file" value="component.py" />
        <argument name="source" value="anduril_custom_functions.py" />
    </launcher>
    <requires URL="http://www.python.org/" name="Python" optional="false" type="manual">python</requires>
    <requires URL="https://code.google.com/p/cutadapt/" name="Cutadapt" optional="false" type="manual">cutadapt</requires>
    <type-parameters>
        <type-parameter name="Cutadapt_info" extends="Log">
            <doc>Cutadapt-specific information file format.</doc>
        </type-parameter>
        <type-parameter name="Cutadapt_report" extends="Log">
            <doc>Cutadapt-specific report file format.</doc>
        </type-parameter>
    </type-parameters>
    <inputs>
        <input name="INFILE_input" type="FASTX" optional="false" array="false">
            <doc>Input file in FASTX (FASTQ or FASTA) format.</doc>
        </input>
        <input name="INFILE_input_mate" type="FASTX" optional="true" array="false">
            <doc>Second (mate) input file (FASTX) for paired-end sequencing libraries.</doc>
        </input>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <output name="OUTFILE_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write modified reads to FILE. FASTQ or FASTA format is chosen depending on input.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_report" type="Cutadapt_report" array="false">
            <doc>Write report.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_too_short_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write reads that are too short (according to length specified by --minimum-length) to FILE (default: discard reads).</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_too_long_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write reads that are too long (according to length specified by --maximum-length) to FILE (default: discard reads).</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_untrimmed_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write reads that do not contain the adapter to FILE (default: output to same file as trimmed reads).</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_info_file" type="Cutadapt_info" array="false">
            <doc>Write information about each read and its adapter matches into FILE. See the documentation for the file format.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_rest_file" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>When the adapter matches in the middle of a read, write the rest (after the adapter) into FILE.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_wildcard_file" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>When the adapter has wildcard bases (&apos;N&apos;s), write adapter bases matching wildcard positions to FILE. When there are indels in the alignment, this will often not be accurate.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_paired_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write second read in a pair to FILE.</doc>
        </output>
        <output name="OUTFILE_untrimmed_paired_output" type="FASTX" array="false">
            <doc>Write the second read in a pair to this FILE when no adapter was found in the first read. Use this option together with --untrimmed-output when trimming paired-end reads (default: output to same file as trimmed reads).</doc>
        </output>
    </outputs>
    <parameters>
        <parameter name="_executable" type="string" default="cutadapt">
            <doc>Path to executable.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_execMode" type="string" default="none">
            <doc>Execution mode. One of &apos;remote&apos;, &apos;local&apos; or &apos;none&apos;.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_cores" type="string" default="1">
            <doc>Number of threads.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_membycore" type="string" default="1500M">
            <doc>Memory per core. Integer, optionally followed by one the follow suffixes: K, M, G.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_runtime" type="string" default="6:00:00">
            <doc>Runtime in h:mm:ss.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_too_short_output" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--too-short-output". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_too_long_output" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--too-long-output". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_untrimmed_output" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--untrimmed-output". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_info_file" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--info-file". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_rest_file" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--rest-file". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_wildcard_file" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--wildcard-file". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_paired_output" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--paired-output". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="_OUTFILE_untrimmed_paired_output" type="boolean" default="false">
            <doc>Switch for enabling the optional output port "--untrimmed-paired-output". Set to true in workflow file if this output is desired.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="no_indels" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Do not allow indels in the alignments (allow only mismatches). Currently only supported for anchored adapters.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="match_read_wildcards" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Allow IUPAC wildcards in reads.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="discard_trimmed" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Discard reads that contain the adapter instead of trimming them. Also use --overlap in order to avoid throwing away too many randomly matching reads.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="discard_untrimmed" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Discard reads that do not contain the adapter.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="no_trim" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Match and redirect reads to output/untrimmed-output as usual, but do not remove adapters.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="trim_n" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Trim N&apos;s on ends of reads.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="mask_adapter" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Mask adapters with &apos;N&apos; characters instead of trimming them.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="quiet" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Do not print a report at the end.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="colorspace" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Colorspace mode: Also trim the color that is adjacent to the found adapter.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="double_encode" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>When in colorspace, double-encode colors (map 0,1,2,3,4 to A,C,G,T,N).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="trim_primer" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>When in colorspace, trim primer base and the first color (which is the transition to the first nucleotide).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="strip_f3" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>For colorspace: Strip the _F3 suffix of read names.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="maq" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>MAQ-compatible colorspace output. This enables --colorspace, --double-encode, --trim-primer, --strip-f3 and --suffix &apos;/1&apos;.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="bwa" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>BWA-compatible colorspace output. This enables --colorspace, --double-encode, --trim-primer, --strip-f3 and --suffix &apos;/1&apos;.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="no_zero_cap" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Do not change negative quality values to zero. Colorspace quality values of -1 would appear as spaces in the output FASTQ file. Since many tools have problems with that, negative qualities are converted to zero when trimming colorspace data. Use this option to keep negative qualities.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="format" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Input file format; can be either &apos;fasta&apos;, &apos;fastq&apos; or &apos;sra-fastq&apos;. Ignored when reading csfasta/qual files (default: auto-detect from file name extension).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="maximum_length" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Discard trimmed reads that are longer than LENGTH. Reads that are too long even before adapter removal are also discarded. In colorspace, an initial primer is not counted (default: no limit).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="minimum_length" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Discard trimmed reads that are shorter than LENGTH. Reads that are too short even before adapter removal are also discarded. In colorspace, an initial primer is not counted (default: 0).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="quality_cutoff" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Trim low-quality bases from 5&apos; and/or 3&apos; ends of reads before adapter removal. If one value is given, only the 3&apos; end is trimmed. If two comma-separated cutoffs are given, the 5&apos; end is trimmed with the first cutoff, the 3&apos; end with the second. The algorithm is the same as the one used by BWA (see documentation) (default: no trimming).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="prefix" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Add this prefix to read names.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="suffix" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Add this suffix to read names.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="length_tag" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Search for TAG followed by a decimal number in the name of the read (description/comment field of the FASTA or FASTQ file). Replace the decimal number with the correct length of the trimmed read. For example, use --length-tag &apos;length=&apos; to correct fields like &apos;length=123&apos;.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="error_rate" type="string" default="0.1">
            <doc>Maximum allowed error rate (no. of errors divided by the length of the matching region; default: 0.1).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="times" type="string" default="1">
            <doc>Try to remove adapters at most COUNT times. Useful when an adapter gets appended multiple times (default: 1).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="max_n" type="string" default="0.1">
            <doc>The max proportion of N&apos;s allowed in a read. A number &lt; 1 will be treated as a proportion while a number &gt; 1 will be treated as the maximum number of N&apos;s contained (default: 0.1).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="overlap" type="string" default="2">
            <doc>Minimum overlap length. If the overlap between the read and the adapter is shorter than LENGTH, the read is not modified. This reduces the number of bases trimmed purely due to short random adapter matches (default: 2).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="quality_base" type="string" default="33">
            <doc>Assume that quality values are encoded as ascii(quality + QUALITY_BASE). The default (33) is usually correct, except for reads produced by some versions of the Illumina pipeline, where this should be set to 64 (default: 33).</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="adapter" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Sequence of an adapter that was ligated to the 3&apos; end. The adapter itself and anything that follows is trimmed. If the adapter sequence ends with the &apos;$&apos; character, the adapter is anchored to the end of the read and only found if it is a suffix of the read.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="front" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Sequence of an adapter that was ligated to the 5&apos; end. If the adapter sequence starts with the character &apos;^&apos;, the adapter is &apos;anchored&apos;. An anchored adapter must appear in its entirety at the 5&apos; end of the read (it is a prefix of the read). A non-anchored adapter may appear partially at the 5&apos; end, or it may occur within the read. If it is found within a read, the sequence preceding the adapter is also trimmed. In all cases, the adapter itself is trimmed.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="anywhere" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Sequence of an adapter that was ligated to the 5&apos; or 3&apos; end. If the adapter is found within the read or overlapping the 3&apos; end of the read, the behavior is the same as for the --adapter option. If the adapter overlaps the 5&apos; end (beginning of the read), the initial portion of the read matching the adapter is trimmed, but anything that follows is kept.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="A" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>3&apos; adapter to be removed from the second read in a pair.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="G" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>5&apos; adapter to be removed from the second read in a pair.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="B" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>5&apos;/3 adapter to be removed from the second read in a pair.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="strip_suffix" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Remove this suffix from read names if present. Can be given multiple times.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="cut" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Remove LENGTH bases from the beginning or end of each read. If LENGTH is positive, the bases are removed from the beginning of each read. If LENGTH is negative, the bases are removed from the end of each read. This option can be specified twice if the LENGTHs have different signs.</doc>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="U" type="string" default="{{FALSE}}">
            <doc>Remove LENGTH bases from the beginning or end of each read (see --cut).</doc>
        </parameter>
    </parameters>
</component>
